+ 1 408 813 5156 | gurutii@gmail.com

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/gurusubramaniams GitHub: https://github.com/gurusubramaniam

Portfolio: Https://www.gurutii.me

## PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Architectural engineering leader who develops engineers through coaching, mentoring, and leading by example. Experienced in managing engineers across the entire stack. Managerial reputation for being accessible, helpful, and encouraging professional growth. Experienced in software delivery management, product and program management, and solution architecture. Excels at building systems while balancing time to market, usability, and technical architecture. Strategic and results-driven with a passion for problem-solving.

## **SKILLS**

Solution creation | Automation | Product development | Project management | Problem-solving | Team leadership | Scrum Master | Diversity and inclusion | Consumer Onboarding | Performance & Talent Management | Change Management | Strategic Thinking

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

React.js | Next.js | Node.js | Typescript | JavaScript | Redux | HTML5 / CSS3 | GraphQL/APIs | LESS | Webpack | Nemo.js | Cypress | Jenkins CI/CD | Python (Beginner) | AWS (Beginner)

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **Hyphen Care (HealthFirst) - Consultant**

May 2023 - Current

## Sr Engineering Manager

- Build SAAS for community health program manager
- Orchestrate and manage Operational and DevOps excellence through the implementation of Agile ceremonies, Jira task management, code versioning, and workflow for CI/CD.
- Set up ITIL best practices for alerting and monitoring-driven incident, change, and problem management.
- People leadership, mentoring, and career planning through regular cadence meetings with engineers to understand their skillsets and provide opportunities.
- Identify and act as a bridge between Hyphen Healthcare, understand the uber-level process, and best practices followed and bring in those practices to the CHPM team.
- Contribute to highly scalable system architecture and build best-of-class SaaS products for our B2B clients.
- Bring in the change control management process.

### PayPal - San Jose, CA

2011-2023

Engineering Manager - Level 2

Apr 2018 - May 2023

### Team - Regulatory Change Management

- Led a team of software engineers (Web, iOS, Android, Java, and QA), in planning and executing software development projects in cross-functional collaboration with product, UX, and business stakeholders.
- Led product launch for 1099-K to collect SSN for compliance with new IRS law for non-compliant users.
- Led and managed the project to add Israel, Russia, and Thailand operational licenses resulting in YoY revenue of \$40 mn.
- Consolidated multiple product workflows to reduce integration support by 50% and improve the user conversion rate by 10%.
- Managed project for account balance provisioning (PayPal Balance) to access money during checkout and P2P transactions.
- Developed consistent CFPB disclosure and fee experience, allowing the company to avoid \$25M user lawsuit.
- Provided architectural leadership and End to End solutions guidance to architects to ensure scalable and reusable software aligned with the company's technical and security standards.
- Played the role of Scrum Master, collaborating with UX, Analytics, and Product team on product decisions and designs.
- Collaborated with peer engineering managers on identifying best practices, improved team processes, and scalable solutions with
  minimal coding that were used for alerting, and monitoring failures and errors in production for both front-end and back-end systems...
- Instituted 1:1 weekly meetings to align engineers' career paths with their interests.

# Team - Shopping

- Built, led, hired, and managed a high-performance team of software engineers (Web, iOS, Android, Java, and QA).
- Provided architectural, people leadership, and End to End technical solutions guidance for the launch of a Shopping Platform for 450M customers (React, LESS, Redux, Node.js).

- Integrated Honey shopping transaction and dispute process with PayPal ecosystem, improved user engagement from 20M to 70M, and saved consumers \$100M through a rewards redemption program in year one.
- Added 2,000 new validated offers from Honey to new coupon redemption checkout experience where coupon use increased by 1.5%.
- Developed a new cashback points program redeemable through PayPal balance or gift cards.
- Managed resources, solutions, and delivery of web applications using React, LESS, Redux, Node.js, and back-end systems.
- Supported LTR and RTL (I10n) representation on web apps and ensured accessibility (a11y) and usable web apps by building testing into the software development and delivery process. This reduced engineering time by 25%.
- Reduced hiring costs by 20% and increased hiring velocity by 40% for in-demand engineers by partnering with leadership to source personnel from Canada, India, and Mexico.
- Ensured that the team had the necessary tools, resources, and infrastructure to be productive.
- Played the role of Scrum Master, collaborating with UX, Analytics, and Product team on product decisions and designs.

#### Team - Onboarding

- Led, mentored, and managed a 6-member team for the successful launch of the PayPal consumer onboarding web experience available in 250 countries for 6 different onboarding workflows in a single year.
- Introduced the concept of "nano-sized" code, optimizing coding assets from 1.2 MB to 600 kb (~67kb zip) with versioning to create sharable isomorphic UI components. This "nano-code" promotes reusability, consistency, and modularity across different workflows.
- Provided architectural leadership and an elegantly simple solution of configuration-driven reusable components for consumption by constituent upstream/downstream applications in the product ecosystem.
- Designed and embedded interaction analytics to parse and transform raw interaction data into structured data for analysis and action.
- Played the role of Scrum Master, collaborating with UX, Analytics, and Product team on product decisions and designs.
- 337K Net New Active accounts Annualized.
- Additional 10 product offerings brought to Unified Onboarding platform.
- Increase in Accessibility Score from 80% to 100%.
- 15% Decrease in Consumer Perceived latency.
- 75 % Development time reduction.

#### Member of Technical Staff - Level 1

July 2016 - Apr 2018

## Team - Onboarding

- Excelled as a mentor, lead, and key contributor in a 6-member team.
- Increased user conversion rate and developer productivity by pitching and implementing onboarding workflow unification.
- Reduced engineering time by 75% through a new architecture that supports flexible, easy-to-configure server-driven UI. Implemented server-driven UI (using GraphQL back-end) to reduce overall engineering time by 75% (page design) and empower constituent app and product owners to run different experiments in different templates at the same time (multiple experimentation platforms) and update the UI for their consumers within hours (replacing week-long manual process) with minimal styling code changes and without having to release the entire web app.
- Reduced engineering effort by 30%, increased time to market by 50%, and decreased production downtime by 30% by creating configuration-driven reusable components.

# Software Engineer III

Mar 2014 - Jul 2016

# Team - Consumer and Partner Onboarding

- Modernized frontend stack from Dust.js to React.js using emerging technologies (React, Redux, and SASS). Built onboarding flows in Node.js from Java.
- Engaged with Consumer and Partner onboarding as a full stack javascript engineer.
- Increased user conversion and activation by adding a card, bank, and credit flow to onboarding.

### Senior User Interface Engineer II

Nov 2011 - Mar 2014

## Team - Consumer Onboarding

- Worked on Node.js, CSS3, and Dust.js, executed Rapid Prototyping, and worked on the user wallet app.
- Worked on user experiences for onboarding users and VDC, credit applications, BML, and debit applications.
- Introduced mobile user Checkout experiences using a rendering engine powered by a 3rd party company.

#### CSC - Chennai, India

Oct 2006 - Oct 2011

Software Engineer for Paypal Projects.

### **EDUCATION**